<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Further newes from Ostend Wherein is declared such accidnets as haue happened since the former edition, dilligently collected out of sundry letters and aduertisments, as haue beene from Zeland, Callice, and other places latley receiued. 1601.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1601</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08576</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18894</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121010</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856201</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856201</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21728</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08576)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21728)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1637:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Further newes from Ostend Wherein is declared such accidnets as haue happened since the former edition, dilligently collected out of sundry letters and aduertisments, as haue beene from Zeland, Callice, and other places latley receiued. 1601.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by V. S[immes] for Thomas Pauier, and are to be sold at his shop in Cornehill, at the signe of the Catte and two Parrots,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ostend (Belgium) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21728:1"/>
            <p>Further Newes of Oſtend. Wherein is declared ſuch accidents <hi>as haue happened ſince the former</hi> Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, dilligently Collected out of ſundry Letters and aduertiſments<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as haue beene from <hi>Zeland, Callice,</hi> and other places, lately receiued. 1601.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by V.S. for Thomas Pauier, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Cornehill, at the ſigne of the Catte and two Parrots. 1601.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21728:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21728:2"/>
            <head>Further Newes of Oſtend.</head>
            <head type="sub">Wherein is declared ſuch accidents <hi>as haue happened ſince the former</hi> Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, dilligently Collected out of ſundry Letters and aduertiſments, as haue beene from <hi>Zeland, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,</hi> and other places, lately receiued.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath béene declared in the former Booke, Intituled, <hi>The Oppugnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Oſtend,</hi> that this Towne hath heretofore diuers times been attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and beſeeged by the common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, but (Gods name be praiſed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) all was in vaine, firſt it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged by the Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> in the yeere of our Lord God <hi>1583.</hi> then by <hi>Monſieur la Motte,</hi> Gouernor of <hi>Graueling,</hi> in the yéere of our Lord God <hi>1585,</hi> who were long before ſollicited and importunated therevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by the continuall ſute and exclamations of the Flemings, who forgot not to labor and inſtigate the Duke of <hi>Burgundi</hi> alſo, euer ſince his comming into the lowe Countries to this péece of worke, ſpecially in the yéere <hi>1596.</hi> after he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the ſtrong Towne of <hi>Callice,</hi> promiſing great ſummes of money towardes the ſame charge, and paying ſome parte thereof into the Dukes treaſury before hand. But the duke knowing that others had attempted the ſame before him with ill ſucceſſe, doubted the like might happen to himſelfe, whereby the glorie of his former victories might be darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:
<pb facs="tcp:21728:3"/>and therefore ſuffered the matter, at that time, to ſléepe. Wherefore they of <hi>Flaunders</hi> (to auoyde the incurſions of the ſouldiers of <hi>Oſtend,</hi> and payment of contribution) tooke apportunitie of the preſent time, whileſt the States forces were imployed at <hi>Bommel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> in the yeere of our Lord <hi>1599,</hi> and made round about the Towne ſundry fortes and tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches for the better aſſuraunce of the paſſages. Yet finding (ſince the making of them) that the charges of thoſe garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſpoyle made in all places of <hi>Flaunders,</hi> by their owne ſouldiers, did farre exceede their former loſſes ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by their ennemies, haue (with much more importuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie than at any time before) ſollicited their Duke to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this their honorable ſute, promiſing (beſides manie other neceſſarie ſeruices during the time of the ſiege) to pay him thirty thouſand pounds ſtarling monthly towardes his charges, and afterwardes (if hee tooke the Towne) nine thouſand poundes ſtarling euery month for the ſpace of twoo yeeres next following. And while they made all theſe gay and liberall promiſes, they forgate not to alleadge vnto the Duke alſo, that nowe, euen at this preſent was the fitteſt time to take in hand this moſt glorious enterpriſe, that had béene offered theſe many yéeres, and might be accompliſhed by his Highneſſe with much leſſe difficulty, than by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gouernour before him, and that therefore hée ought in no wiſe to let ſlippe ſo fitte opportunitie, the like whereof, without all doubt, was not to be hoped for in many yéeres to come, and perhappes, not ſo long as hee liued: for they had certayne intelligence, that the Towne was ſlenderly furniſhed with ſouldiers, and much woorſe with powder, ſhotte, and ordonance, and no victualles in the Towne to ſerue thoſe few ſouldiers eight dayes: and further (which was the chéeſeſt matter, and of greateſt conſequence among all other) <hi>Graue Maurice</hi> with all the States forces was nowe before the Towne of <hi>Bercke</hi> in Dutchland, which his
<pb facs="tcp:21728:3"/>Highneſſe hadde, with great foreſight ſufficiently proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for, with more than a competent garriſon, and al other neceſſaries fitte for the defence thereof, from whence the States forces, nor any parte thereof coulde be brought in ſo ſhort a time, but that by a ſodayne attempt againſt <hi>Oſtend,</hi> he might, not onely breake, and make fruſtrate, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of the ennemy before <hi>Bercke,</hi> who (without all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion) woulde, in all haſte, raiſe his ſiege there, with ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, to ſpeede himſelfe towardes <hi>Flaunders</hi>) and yet looſe <hi>Oſtend,</hi> before hee ſhoulde be able to come ſo farre with his forces, in any due time to ſuccour the ſame.</p>
            <p>And further added heere unto, that he was ſure of one ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage in this ſiege, for that they of <hi>Oſtend,</hi> neyther had, nor could haue any horſe, to incounter with his forces, and therefore his horſemen would ſo bridle the towne, that they ſhoulde not once dare to iſſue out of the Gates, nor to offer ſkirmiſh, or if they did, his horſemen would eaſily ouerrunne them, and cauſe them to retire.</p>
            <p>The Duke not ignorant how commodious and honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the taking of this Towne would be vnto him, mooued partely by theſe reaſons, but eſpecially by the want of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to pacifie the mutined ſouldiers of diuers places, and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the greater likelihood of greater diſcontentment to hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen among his other ſouldiers and garriſons (with whom he was behinde hand for aboue thirtie months pay) thought it ſitteſt for the preſent time, and moſt acceptable to his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects generally, to imploy his ſouldiers in this halfe hopeleſſe attempt, where hée might (not with money) but with his ennemies ſword pay a great many of theſe mutinous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions their wages, and preſerue the reſt from the like danger.</p>
            <p>And becauſe ſuch manner of payment may be the better vnderſtoode, it ſhall not be impertinent, to ſhew brieſtly, the manner thereof vſed by the Prieſts, Friars, and race of the
<pb facs="tcp:21728:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>moſt curſed and diabolicall order of Ieſuites, who for the maintenance of their Romiſh Church, perſwade the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſouldiers (as they doe all others in their ſhriftes, and when they lie on their death-beds) to giue liberally to the Church, to the end, that Praters and Dirges may be made, and ſung for their ſoules: ſuch ſouldiers therefore as die, or are ſlayne before they goe to any ſeruice, bequeathe their pay to one monaſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rie, church, or other chappell, all which the Cleargy giueth to the King, or to their Duke, for the maintenance of the warres: and if any ſouldiers bequeathe their pay to their wiues, and children or other friendes, the ſame is neuer, or but very ſeldome payde.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Oſſuna,</hi> beeing Gennerall of the Dukes army was preſently ſent towardes <hi>Oſtend,</hi> and comming before it the fift day of Iuly <hi>ſtilo nouo,</hi> or rather, the fiue and twenty day of Iune, as wee write héere in England, plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his ordonance againſt the eaſt end of the Towne, and the next day beganne to ſhoote and batter downe the houſes: wherevpon <hi>Monſieur Vander Noote,</hi> Gouernor of <hi>Oſtend,</hi> gaue preſent order, that many of the houſes and buildings, ſhould be taken downe and defaced, and the ſtréetes vnpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, to the end that the enemies ſhot might the leſſe offend the people and ſouldiers within the walls: and commaunded alſo, that al the women and children ſhould be ſent out of the towne into <hi>Zeland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The nine and twenty day were <hi>28.</hi> companies of ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſent into the towne from <hi>Zeland,</hi> with great plenty of victualles, and all other munition, fitte for the defence of the Towne. And the next day following, ſir <hi>Francis Vere</hi> came to <hi>Oſtend</hi> with eight companies of Engliſh men, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently entrenched himſelfe without the Towne on the ſouth ſide vnder the walles, which was the onely place and fitteſt péece of ground, from whence the enemy might, with his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, batter the walles, and hath euer ſince kept the ſame in
<pb facs="tcp:21728:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>deſpite of all the ennemies force, with eightéene or twentie companies, who daily haue giuen, and doe giue the enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſufficient worke, to his great loſſe, and ſlaughter of his beſt and braueſt ſouldiers, as hath partely béene before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in the former Edition, whereunto I referre the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reader: yet thus much I thought good briefly to note by the way, for the better ſatiſfaction of all ſuch as haue not read the ſame. Since which time hath béene written ſundry aduertiſements, as well from <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> and <hi>Callice,</hi> as alſo from <hi>Zeland</hi> and other places, which I haue collected in this preſent Pamphlet, for the further contentment of all ſuch as are deſirous to reade and vnderſtand the ſame.</p>
            <p>THe enemy obſtinately continuing his ſlege before <hi>Oſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end,</hi> &amp; they likewiſe of the Towne with like reſolution defending the ſame, all means poſſible, and warlike ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems, to anoy, or defend, are dayly put in practiſe: the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie with his ordonance thinketh to wearie them of the Towne, killing ſometimes <hi>5.6.7.</hi> and <hi>8.</hi> men in a day, for he ſéeth it a thing vnpoſſible to bring his ordonance ſo neere the walls as to make a breach: they of the Towne forget not to repay him triple intereſt with their cannon, though not with ſo many ſhot, yet with the death of foure and fiue of their enemies for one ſlayne of theirs.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Oſſuna</hi> vexed dayly with the continuall iſſuings and ſkirmiſhings more then he deſireth, and great ſlaughter of his people: and finding the great inconuenience of the ground, for the ſpéedie bringing of his people from the Eaſt fort to the weſt fort to ſuccor each other, as néede re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, hath with ſtraw, fagots, hauen, and earth, made a cawſey from <hi>Albertus</hi> forte to the eaſt fort, betwéene the walls of the Towne and his fortes, yet far without danger of the ſhotte from the Towne, and hath alſo brought all his ordenance from the eaſt ſide, and planted the ſame againſt
<pb facs="tcp:21728:5"/>the weſt ſide of the Towne.</p>
            <p>The States horſmen which came from the ſlege of <hi>Berk,</hi> vnderſtanding that <hi>500</hi> Spaniards were ſent out of <hi>Dieſt,</hi> and were marching towards the Dukes campe, made ſuch haſte after them, that they ouer tooke them, &amp; fierſly aſſailing them on al ſides, put them all to the ſword, except ſome few which eſcaped by flight to carry newes of their ill hap.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Frances Vere</hi> was hurt in the necke, and bruiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue his ſhoulder, ſo that his forehead was therwith ſwoln, which hapned with the ſplinter of a carriage that was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by a ſhotte from the enemies: but the hurte (as God woulde) is not great, neither is his perſon in any daunger thereby, although it was at the firſt ſomewhat troubleſome vnto him. But within few dayes after hée departed from <hi>Oſtend,</hi> to <hi>Middleborough,</hi> to conferre with his Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and the States, about theſe affaires, who are daily loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for to come thither, where they meane to make theyr abode, during the time of this ſéege, to the end they may with more expedition giue order in theſe weighty affaires.</p>
            <p>The <hi>1200.</hi> men that were preſſed out of <hi>Kent, Eſſex,</hi> and other places of <hi>England,</hi> and had laine at <hi>Vluſhing,</hi> are ſent to <hi>Oſtend,</hi> with <hi>3000.</hi> other old ſouldiers, all <hi>Wallons,</hi> and <hi>Scots,</hi> ſo that there lieth within the towne, and in the tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches without, ſome <hi>8000.</hi> men beſides <hi>3000.</hi> more, which lie in ſhippes of warre before the towne, ready to be landed vpon any occaſion, who are daily ſupplyed with all kinde of Munition, and freſh victualles, in ſo much, that all victuals ſitte for ſouldiers, are there ſolde very aboundantly, and at reaſonable priſes, neither doe the ſouldiers want money, but are very well payde, whereby they may prouide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of all ſuch neceſſaries as they want, and if any fall ſicke, or are hurte, they are preſently ſent out of the towne, to <hi>Vluſhing, Middleborough,</hi> and other places of <hi>Zeland,</hi> where they are placed in the Hoſpitalles, and are ſo dilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently
<pb facs="tcp:21728:5"/>attended, and carefully looked vnto, as themſelues can wiſh or deſire, wanting neither meate, drincke, wine, phyſicke, nor ſurgerie, nor whatſoeuer elſe is fitte and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for their health and recouerie, but are cheriſhed as if they were in their fathers houſes: ſurely a moſt godly, and chriſtian deed of the people of thoſe countries, who (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their continuall taxations laid vpon them for the maintenance of theſe long warres) do moſt liberally, and fréely contribute euery man according to his eſtate and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>billity in this moſt charitable action, which is a worthy mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to vs, and to all other chriſtians, teaching vs to eſtéeme of the poore, and ſpecially to haue a fatherly care of the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, who (while we ſléepe quietly in our beddes, and goe without feare about our worldly affaires at home) muſt watch and ward day and night in all wethers, and as often as he ſhall be by his captaine commaunded, venture his life againſt the enemie, and as a bulwarke, ſtand betwéene the enemy and vs for the defence of our liues, wiues, children, goods, and cuntry.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Horatio Vere</hi> hauing commaund in his brothers ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, vpon Tueſday being the ninth day of Auguſt, offered ſkirmiſh to the ennemy which was long &amp; fiercely continued on both ſides, and diuers times ſupplied with freſh ſupplies, wherein the enemie loſt <hi>400</hi> men, beſides many that were hurt: and but ten ſouldiers of the Towne ſlayne, and ſuch as haue lately come from <hi>Callice,</hi> ſay, that the Flemmings themſelues reported there, that there were ſéene <hi>84</hi> wagons with ſick and hurt men carried out of the campe. In this fight the ordonance of the Towne ſlew many, both horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and footmen, and as it was reported by marchants of good credit, there were in this fight ſéene <hi>4</hi> and <hi>5</hi> horſemen killed with one ſhot from the Towne, and ſometimes, <hi>10</hi> and <hi>12</hi> footmen and more, were ſéene to be torne and carried away with one bullet.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21728:6"/>
            <p>If the enemy finde many ſuch banquets before <hi>Oſtend,</hi> I thinke he will quickly be weary of his fare, and ſéeke a more friendly hoaſt elſewhere: and furthermore they report, that it is incredible, to ſée and heare what great numbers of dead men are daily brought from the campe, to all the Townes and Villages néere adioyning to the Campe to be buried, moſt of them being Spaniardes, and Italians, Captaines, Alferoes, and other Commaunders, whereof many are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in Friers wéedes with great ſolempnitie, ſaying and ſinging of Maſſes and Dirges for their ſoules, God graunt we heare no woorſe newes of their fellowes.</p>
            <p>They of <hi>Flaunders</hi> (vnderſtanding that the horſemen of the States were come to <hi>Bargen vp Zome,</hi> and ſome of the footemen into <hi>Zeland,</hi> where the count <hi>Maurice</hi> was dayly expected, doubting that his Excellencie was purpoſed to land his forces in the land of <hi>Waſte,</hi> with intent to ouerrun the country thereabout with fire and ſword) gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all the Boores and Peſants of the countrey in Armes, and haue carryed what they could into the townes and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſtrength.</p>
            <p>The twelfth day of Auguſt was an other great fight with the enemy, the ſame continued an houre and more, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded with freſh ſupplies on both ſides, ſometimes the one parte, ſometimes the other giuing ground, and the ordo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Towne playing vpon the enemies where they were ſéene to be thickeſt: in all mens iudgement there were ſlayne thrée hundred and more of the ennemy, beſides many that were hurt, and there were <hi>32.</hi> of our men ſlayne, and ſome few hurt.</p>
            <p>There was a Mariner of <hi>Zeland</hi> in <hi>Oſtend,</hi> that had his legge ſtricken off with a great ſhot, who was taken vp to be carried to the ſhippe, but before hee could be brought to the boate, hée was with an other ſhotte ſtrucke thorow the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that he preſently dyed, and ſo was rid of his paine. The
<pb facs="tcp:21728:6"/>like hapned at an other time to a ſouldier that was likewiſe ſlayne with the enemies great ſhotte, and being carried on foure mens ſhoulders to the graue, the coffin and corſe were ſhot thorow with an other bullet, the men preſently ſet the coffin on the ground, and ranne as faſt as they coulde, ſtriu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing who ſhould firſt get the ſhot.</p>
            <p>Thurſeday the <hi>13.</hi> day was a ſhip caled the <hi>Globe</hi> of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi> met before <hi>Oſtend,</hi> laden very richly, and is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, to be woorth <hi>4.</hi> millions, which came from the riuer of <hi>Plate,</hi> and ſtraights of <hi>Magellanes,</hi> the ſame ſhip had béen out thrée yeeres: and ſuch as met this ſhip in their way from <hi>Vluſhing,</hi> reporte that two M. men more ſhal be ſent out of <hi>Zeland</hi> to <hi>Oſtend,</hi> which will make vp the number of <hi>13.</hi> M. men, beſides the voluntarie, and others lately gone out of <hi>England,</hi> ſo that it ſéemeth ſome great and extraordinary péece of ſeruice is meant: God graunt courage and good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to our people.</p>
            <p>It is written from <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> that the Duke doth woon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders againſt the Towne, and hath ſo beſieged it both by ſea and land, that there is no way left to ſuccour the ſame, and that their Gallies lying before the hauen, haue drouen all the ſhippes of warre from thence, and ſuncke many: and yet (God knowes) the Gallies dare not once peepe out, or ſhew themſelues, for the laſt time they were at ſea, they found (in their returne from <hi>Sluice</hi>) their way ſo dangerous to eſcape their enemies hands, that they haue ſince, had ſmall deſire to hazard themſelues abroade.</p>
            <p>There hath beene ſome ſpéeches, that the enemy made a rowling trench, to fill vp the ditches of the Towne, and ſo meant to enter the Towne ouer the walles, after hée hadde made the ſame of equall height with the walls of the towne, but in truth that ſuppoſed worke, was partly, for the repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his mounte, and making paſſage to frée his ſouloiers from the waters, which mount was ſo continually beaten
<pb facs="tcp:21728:7"/>with the ordonance from the towne, &amp; the workmen ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with the iſſuings and ſkirmiſhings from ſir <hi>Frauncis Veres</hi> trenches, and the towne, that the ſame could neuer be finiſhed: but ſpecially to defend his trenches on the north weſt ſide of the town from the fireworks, which they of <hi>Oſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end</hi> did continually caſt into thoſe trenches, to the great an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyance of the enemy and deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſouldiers therein, which trenches lie within foure or fiue pikes lengths of the counterſcarps of the towne: but if it were ſo, that the enemy could bring ſuch a ſuppoſed trench, without let of waters and lay the ſame leuell with the wall (which great paynes the Duke néede not to put his people vnto, for that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor hath offered to ſet open the Gates, and to let his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple enter if they durſt) the Towne being furniſhed with ſuch a number of men, and many of them olde ſouldiers, the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my would quickely be weary of that enterpriſe: for without all queſtion, they are ſo ſtrong of men within the towne, that if they had but one M. horſe, and fitte ground without the towne, they would not feare, but (with Gods help) to hazard a battel, and peraduenture giue the Duke as hard entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as they did the laſt yéere before <hi>Newport.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There paſſeth few dayes, but there are ſome ſallies and enterpriſes made vpon the enemy, and many men ſlayne on both ſides, but all men that come from thence, <hi>Callice,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, agrée in this, that thee enemy looſeth <hi>4, 5, 6, 7,</hi> and <hi>8.</hi> for one loſt on our ſide: notwithſtanding it is (by good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt kept) written from <hi>Vluſhing,</hi> that there hath beene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue forty M. great ſhot diſcharged againſt the ſowne ſince the firſt beginning of this ſiege, ſo that the weaſt ſide of the wall of the towne ſlicketh ſo full, and ſo thicke of great ſhot, as the like hath not at any time before beene knowne in any ſiege, and yet the Duke is no more likely to obtaine his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, than he was at his firſt comming before the towne.</p>
            <p>The <hi>21.</hi> day there came to <hi>London</hi> a French man from
<pb facs="tcp:21728:7"/>
               <hi>Callice,</hi> who reported for certayne, that the King of <hi>Fraunce</hi> was, in poaſt, come to <hi>Boloigne</hi> the Wedneſday before, and had appoynted to be at <hi>Callice</hi> the next day following, being the twentieth day of this moneth of Auguſt, which reporte hath ſince béene by diuers confirmed, and that it was the <hi>22</hi> day in the euening before he came into <hi>Callice,</hi> and alſo, that charge was giuen by the King, that euery towneſman of the ſea towns ſhould haue, and furniſh himſelfe with ten pound of powder, and ten pound of lead or ſhot. The Frenchman aboueſayd being demaunded concerning <hi>Oſtend,</hi> anſwered, that (thanked be God) al was well, that there was no feare or doubt to be made of the towne, for they wanted nothing, but had all things plentifully fit for their defence and ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and at very reaſonable prices: adding further, that (if any man would accept his offer) he would wager a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred crownes againſt thrée hundred, that the Duke ſhoulde not get <hi>Oſtend,</hi> and be maiſter thereof theſe foure moneths.</p>
            <p>It is alſo written from <hi>Callice,</hi> and confirmed by ſundry which come later from <hi>Vluſhing,</hi> that vpon ſaterday beeing the fiftéenth of Auguſt, the enemy attempting ſome workes néerer to the towne than héeretofore, had many pioners and ſouldiers, to the number of about a thouſand, or more to guarde them, whereupon they ſallied out of ſir <hi>Francis Veres</hi> trenches, and beganne a very hote fight, and were ſeconded preſently with a thouſand footemen out of the Towne, the fight was very hote, and with great fury maintained on both ſides, neyther ſide ſparing the other, but euery one do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his beſt to kil his next enemy: but in the end, the enemies were forced, by the meanes of the artillerie of the towne, to giue backe, whereupon our men followed with ſuch furie, that they forced the enemy, euen to his trenches, with ſlaugh ter of many of them, and followed ſo hard vppon them, that they ſeized ſeauen péeces of ordonance, which though the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy a good while defended, yet in the ende, he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled
<pb facs="tcp:21728:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>pelled to abandon the place. But while our ſouldiers were earneſtly buſied to naile and choake the péeces, a barrell of gunpowder ſtanding neere the ordonance, toke ſuddenly fire by reaſon of a match which the enemies had ſecretly layd of purpoſe to miſchiefe our people, whereby ſome <hi>150</hi> of our ſouldiers were blowne vp, and ſcorched, yet not ſo ſore hurt thereby, but that, with Gods helpe, many of them will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>game recouer, and be able to do good ſeruice. Some reporte that this miſchance hapned by one of the preſſed ſouldiers, comming too néere the powder with his match, but howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it hapned, the enemie preſently hereupon came afreſh vpon our ſouldiers, who being amazed with this ſuddayne miſhap, and many not knowing what it meant, were forced to retire, but there were ſlaine of the enemies in the fight <hi>2000.</hi> men whereof thrée. C. and more were horſemen, beſides thrée C. pioners, neither was this victorie gotten without loſſe on our ſide, for there were ſlaine of our men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>4.</hi> hundred, and néere thrée hundred hurt and ſcorched.</p>
            <p>The gouernour of the Towne ſéeing the enemie to vſe all meanes poſſible to approach néerer to the walles, hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the hauen ditch or banke on the ſouthweſt ſide of the Towne to be cut, thorow which floweth ſuch aboundance of water at full ſea, that the ſame runneth a league into the land, euen to the forte of <hi>Iſabella,</hi> which doth ſo amaze and terrifie the enemie, and all the cuntry thereabouts, that it is coniectured the enemie will not lie long before <hi>Oſtend,</hi> for the firſt northweſt wind that bloweth with any great gale, will cauſe the water to ſpred and ouerflow the cuntry much farther, and the cutting of the banke, cauſeth ſuch a ſeperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betwéen the trenches of both ſides, at hie water, that they can not come one to the other by eight or nine ſcore, for ſixe houres ſpace, neither with horſe nor footemen.</p>
            <p>It is reported by a ſouldier which came the fouretéenth day of this moneth out of <hi>Oſtend,</hi> that they fight and iſſue
<pb facs="tcp:21728:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>out of the towne vpon the enemy daily, and that there is no want of any thing in the towne: that the new way made for ſmall ſhipping to come to the towne cut out of the head, was againe ſtopped and made<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vp, for feare of ſuch inconuenience as might thereby happen to the towne thorow tempeſtuous weather. And that for the better aſſurance of ſhipping com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in by the olde Hauen, ſir <hi>Frauncis Vere</hi> had cauſed a mount to be raiſed ioyning vnto the Hauen, whereuppon the enemies ordonance playeth continually: but they of the towne doe likewiſe continually repaire &amp; make vp the ſame againe. And alſo he reported that ſome parte of the enemies trenches towardes the northweſt, lay within foure or fiue pikes lengths of the townes counterſcarps, as is before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, &amp; ſome other part of the trenches within eight or ten ſcore of ours, the greateſt part lay much farther off. That the water ranne euery tide a great breadth betweene the towne, and the enemies, ſo that in many of their trenches the enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie ſtoode aboue the knées continually in water, and at a ſpring tide the waters reached aboue their nauilles, euen to their breaſts, which waters, they of the towne with a ſluice had deuiſed to kéepe in, that with the ebbe the ſame coulde not return: at the firſt the trenches of the towne were annoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the ſame waters, aſwell as the enemies: but ſince, they haue found remedy to kéep the waters out of their own trenches. But the enemies are ſo greatly vexed with theſe waters, that they are oftentimes forced to goe out of their trenches, and to ſit or lie vpon the banks and perapets: and then the ordonaunce of the Towne playeth ſo vehemently vpon them, that many of their carkaſſes are carried into the ayre: and further, the ſayde ſouldier affirmed, that it was a thing vnpoſſible for the enemy to get the towne, as long as men, victualles, and munition might be brought in, which the enemie ſhoulde neuer be able to lette, though his ſhotte might cauſe ſome ſmall danger in the day time, ſaying, that
<pb facs="tcp:21728:9"/>if once rayne and fowle weather came, it was not poſſible that the enemy could kéepe his trenches, but muſt be forced to abnandon the ſame.</p>
            <p>The fiue and twentieth day of Auguſt were two ſallies made vpon the enemy, with great ſlaughter, for after the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies were drouen out of their trenches, and with great fury followed, the horſemen came in ſo great troupes vpon our people, that they were forced to retire: but within two houres after, they iſſued the ſecond time (after they had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ordonance of the towne to be laden with muſket ſhot, and dice or ſquare ſhot, imagining that the horſmen (as they did before, would with great troupes ſuccour their footemen) and with great reſolution charged the enemy, and as they had done before, cauſed them to forſake their trenches: and following hard vpon them, the horſemen (as was imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) came vpon our people, who with their pikes and muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets galled them ſhrewdly: but retyring in order, to bring them within the daunger of the townes ordonaunce, which were ſo well beſtowed vpon them, that lanes were made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the thickeſt, and at laſt foure hundred horſemen ſlayne.</p>
            <p>The count <hi>Maurice</hi> came to <hi>Middleborough</hi> the one and twentieth day of this moneth, the reſt of his forces came from <hi>Dort</hi> in <hi>Holland</hi> with eight hundred ſaile great and ſmall, but where he mindeth to employ the ſame, is vnkno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen: God for his mercie ſake (who is the giuer of all good things) graunt him victorie and good ſucceſſe whereſoeuer he goeth, and to all his enterpriſes: and contrariwiſe, confound the tyrannicall attempts of the bloody Papiſts, and of all their diabolicall and moſt wicked procéedings. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS,</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21728:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
